Sargent, Charles Sprague, 1841-1927. Records of the Director Charles Sprague Sargent, 1893-1927 (inclusive): A Finding Aid.
Records of the Director Charles Sprague Sargent, 1893-1927 (inclusive).
Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University, Jamaica Plain, MA 02130.
IB CSS.
Charles Sprague Sargent, 1841-1927.
20 Boxes.
The archival collection consists of administrative files of Charles Sprague Sargent as director of the Arnold Arboretum, including both letterpress copybooks and incoming correspondence. Material pertains to fund raising for collecting expeditions to China, Korea, Japan, and Tibet in the 1910s and 1920s, and to horticulture at the Arboretum. Considerable correspondence exists with John Muir, 1897-1912; Ernest H. Wilson and Joseph Rock concerning their botanical collecting in Asia; and botanists in Europe and the United States.
Access to Finding Aid record in Hollis Classic or Hollis.
Additional Charles Sprague Sargent correspondence can be found by searching the Arnold Arboretum Correspondence Index.
The Charles Sprague Sargent papers were acquired during his 54 year tenure as the first Arnold Arboretum Director. The Papers were originally housed at the first administrative offices of the Arnold Arboretum, located at the Sargent estate, Holm Lea, in a large vacant house. For 12 years the "Dwight house" was the headquarters for Sargent's library and herbarium. In 1892 a permanent building to house the library, herbarium, and administrative offices of the Arboretum was constructed. The final move of the Sargent papers, library and herbarium from the Sargent estate to "the museum," as the building was called for several years, took place late in 1892. They have remained in the Arnold Arboretum Archives since then and were later accessioned into HOLLIS # ACZ8061.
Access:
Researchers seeking to examine archival materials are strongly encouraged to make an appointment. The Director, or an office of origin, may place restrictions on the use of some or all of its records. The extent and length of the restriction will be determined by the Director, office of origin, and the Archivist and will be enforced equally for all researchers.
Charles Sprague Sargent (1841-1927) was the Arnold Arboretum's first director and served the institution for over 54 years. The child of Henrietta Gray and Ignatius Sargent, a successful Boston merchant, banker, and railroad financier, Sargent had the opportunity to pursue a career in science and horticulture. After graduating from Harvard College and serving in the Union army, Sargent spent his first horticultural years abroad touring the gardens of Europe and then at home managing the family estate and gardens of Holm Lea. As a prominent member of the Massachusetts Horticultural Society and an elected trustee of the Massachusetts Society for Promoting Agriculture, Sargent's activities continued to expand. Sargent was appointed director of Harvard's Botanic Garden in 1872. Although the Arnold Arboretum was established in 1872 with Sargent as the first director, his official appointment occurred in 1873.
The Sargent papers include biographical material,correspondence, collection notes, published works, and photographs of Sargent, family, Holm Lea, the Sargent Estate, and colleagues. The correspondence consists of nine volumes of handwritten and typed copies of letters from 1882-1923. Arranged by subject, the volumes do not follow in chronological order. The collected works reflect the activities and development of the Arnold Arboretum from the collaboration of Olmsted and Sargent in the landscape design of the Arboretum, to the exploration, identification, cultivation, and introduction of plant material by the Arnold to other arboreta, nurseries, and the public. Sargent expanded the scope of the Arboretum's influence to include the preservation of the natural landscape, and American forests. Included in the collection are numerous articles on forestry reports, forest fires, and protection of forests, and Sargent's Tenth Census of the United States Forestry, 1880-1883.
The collection is organized into the following series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence 1882-1923
III. Collection Notes
IV. Sargent Publications
V. Books
VI. Sargent Photographs
- I: Biographical Material
  - Career (Box 1:)
  - Folder 1:
    - Rehder, Alfred. 1927. Charles Sprague Sargent. Journal of the Arnold Arboretum 8:68-87.
  - Folder 2:
    - Wilson, Ernest H. June 1927. Charles Sprague Sargent. The Harvard Graduate Magazine 35(140):605-638.
  - Folder 3:
    - April 24, 1941. The One-Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of Charles Sprague Sargent.Arnoldia 1(5):29-32.
  - Folder 4:, Biographical Sketch
    - March 24, 1927. Charles Sprague Sargent. New York Tribune.
    - Trealease, William. 1929. Biographical Memoir of Charles Sprague Sargent. Academy of Sciences Biographical Memoirs.
  - Folder 5:, Charles Sprague Sargent and Forestry
    - Muir, John. July 1908. Sargent's Silva. Atlantic Monthly 92:9-22.
    - Graves, Henry S. November 1921. Dr. Sargent's Contribution to Forestry in America. American Forestry Magazine.
    - Chamberlain, Allen. December 14, 1921. Fifty Years Fighting for Forests. Boston Evening Transcript.
    - Holst, Monterey L. July 1946. The Phantom Work of Professor Sargent's. Journal of Forestry 44(7).
    - Holst, Monterey Leman. "Zachariah Allen, Pioneer in Applied Silviculture."
      Mentions Charles Sprague Sargent and forestry.
    - Forest Flora of Japan. Advertisement.
    - Fazio, James R. "America's Forest Reserves."
    - "Louisiana Forestry Law Goes into Effect."
    - Spongberg, Stephen A. Autumn 1984. C. S. Sargent- Seeing the Forest and the Trees. Orion Nature Quarterly 3(4):5-11.
    - Rosevear, Francis B. December 1984. Charles Sprague Sargent on Loan to the Adirondacks. Adirondack pp.20-23.
    - Raymo, Chet. July 28, 1986. Tree Book as Yankee as a Cod. Boston Globe.
  - Folder 6:, Establishment and Influence of the Arnold Arboretum
    - Duncan, Frances. August 1905. Professor Charles Sprague Sargent and The Arnold Arboretum. The Critic and Literary World 47(2):109-119.
    - March 15, 1917. Work of the Arnold Arboretum Has Much Advanced. The Christian Science Monitor.
    - McFarland, J. Horace. "The Man Who is Making a Tree Garden to Last a Thousand Years - and His Home."
    - Arnold, Frank A. "The Man With the Thousand Year Tree Garden."
    - "Knowledge for Its Own Sake."
    - Geary, Sheila Connor and B. June Hutchinson. August 1979. Revised April 1, 1981. "The Original Design and Permanent Arrangement of the Arnold Arboretum as Determined by Frederick Law Olmsted and Charles Sprague Sargent: A Chronology."
    - Spongberg, Stephen A. April 1996. Charles Sprague Sargent and the Establishment of the Arnold Arboretum.
  - Folder 7:, Obituaries and Memorials
    - June 8, 1927. "Arboretum Service for Professor Sargent."
    - June 9, 1927. Honor Sargent at Arboretum.The Boston Herald.
    - June 9, 1927. Sargent Memorial. Boston Evening Transcript.
    - June 9, 1927. Memorial Tribute to Professor Sargent in Arnold Arboretum, His Creation. The Boston Globe.
    - March 23, 1927. Death of the Head of The Arnold Arboretum. Boston Evening Transcript.
    - March 24, 1927. Charles Sprague Sargent.Boston Herald.
    - March 26, 1927. The Listener. Boston Evening Transcript.
    - May 1927. Professor Charles Sprague Sargent's Funeral to be at Brookline, Friday. Journal of Forestry.
    - "Professor Sargent of Harvard Dies."
    - "Professor Sargent's Funeral is Held."
    - "Charles S. Sargent Buried."
    - "Funeral Services for Professor Sargent."
    - A Great Figure Passes. American Forests.
    - Charles S. Sargent.
      Article begins: "In the death of Charles S. Sargent, ..."
    - Charles Sprague Sargent.
      Article begins: "...of the same Massachusetts family as John Singer Sargent..."
    - Charles S. Sargent Memorial Service. Horticulture Illustrated.
    - Arnold Arboretum Memorial Invitation.
    - An Unfinished Monument. Country Life in America.
  - Folder 8:, Fund-raising in Honor of Charles Sprague Sargent
    - November 5, 1927. Arnold Arboretum Endowment Reaches Half-Million Mark. The Christian Science Monitor.
    - December 2, 1927. "Arboretum Gets $109,250."
    - "Dinner Here Aids Arboretum."
    - "Endowment Sought for Famed Tree Collection."
    - "National Plea Made for Fund for Arboretum."
    - "Arboretum Aid Urged to Honor Charles S. Sargent."
    - NY Drive Begun for Sargent Fund.
    - Arboretum Tests Many New Trees. New York Times p.18.
  - Folder 9:, Charles Sprague Sargent Handwriting Analysis
    - Samuel [sic] Sprague Sargent: An Analysis of His Handwriting.
  - Folder 10:, General Articles / Awards
    - June 9, 1923.The Talk of the Trade.Horticulture.
    - December 15, 1924. Award to Professor Sargent. Horticulture.
    - "Phantom Work of Professor Sargent."
    - "Influential Friends: Charles Sprague Sargent and Louisa Yeomans King."
  - (Box 2:)
  - Folder 1:, Sargent Family
    - Potter, Mary Sargent. Silhouettes: My Mother and Father. SPUR Magazine.
    - Chamberlain, Joseph Edgar. February 16, 1924. An Epitome of New England - The Sargent Family. Boston Evening Transcript.
  - Folder 2:
    - "Charles Sprague Sargent."
      Clipping about the Sargent family and "Epes Sargent and His Descendants."
    - 1921. The Giants of the Sargent Family 1921- Charles Sprague and John Singer Sargent. Photograph.
    - Johnson, Julia Mehitable. "A list of the Publications of the Descendants of Epes Sargent." Reprinted from Epes Sargent of Gloucester and His Descendants.
    - Epes Sargent. Photograph.
    - "Epes Sargent Family Trees."
    - Sutton, S. B. Charles Sprague Sargent and the Arnold Arboretum. Harvard University Press, 1970.
    - Arranged by Emma Worcester Sargent with Biographical Notes by Charles Sprague Sargent. Epes Sargent of Gloucester and His Descendants.
  - Holm Lea Newspaper and Magazine Articles (Box 3:)
  - May 1897. A Suburban Country Place. The Century Magazine 54(1).
  - June 6, 1908. "Charity Bazaar at Holm Lea."
  - November 1, 1904. Holm Lea. Gardening 13(292):49-51. Miller, Wilhelm.
  - March 12, 1911. The Sargent Home Near Boston. Country Life pp.199-208.
  - August 31, 1912. Reproduced photographs of garden, no text. Horticulture.
  - December 19--. Potter, Mary Sargent. Holm Lea - A pioneer American Garden. Countryside Magazine.
  - September 14, 1927. Part of Holm Lea Placed on Market. Boston Herald.
  - September 13, 1927. Holm Lea Offered For Sale. Boston Post.
  - October 1927. Lots on Sargent Estate Mostly Large. Real Estate News.
  - December 3, 1927. Will Develop Sargent Estate so as to Preserve Its Beauty. Boston Evening Transcript.
  - "Employees Check Roof Blaze at Holm Lea."
  - Iris Time in the Garden at Holm Lea. Photograph.
  - Holm Lea Across the Dogwoods. Photograph.
  - A Visit from the Rock Garden. Photograph.
  - "The Sargent Estate Valued at $763,529."
  - February 8, 1946. Letter from E. D. Merrill to Mrs. Guy Lowell.
    A letter discussing the recent death of Miss Alice Sargent and the fate of an oil painting of Professor Charles Sprague Sargent, thought to be still hanging at Holm Lea.
  - Marx, H. August 13, 1993. First Arboretum Director was a Noted Conservationist. Jamaica Plain Gazette.
  - Holm Lea Photographs (Box 3A:)
  - 1897. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Open Terrace. Century Magazine 54(1):6, May 1897.
    Clippings from a photographic essay in Century Magazine on the Estate.
  - 1898. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Narcissus poeticus. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1898. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Berberis thumbergii in front of piazza.
  - 1898. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Viburnum tomentosum var. sterile.
  - 1898. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Viburnum tomentosum var. sterile.
  - 1898. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Trillium grandiflorum
  - 189? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Cornus florida.
  - 1899. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. View across the pond toward residence.
  - 1900. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron catawbiense on a cold winter day. Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1900. Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron catawbiense on a cold winter day. Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - Photo by A. Rehder. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron catawbiense. Normal condition. Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Magnolia denudata with tupelo in background. Estate of one late Prof. Charles Sprague Sargent in Brookline, MA.
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron simsii. Indian azaleas on the terrace of the house.
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Pond. Estate of one late Prof. Charles Sprague Sargent in Brookline, MA.
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Looking across the pond to the house. Estate of the late Prof. Charles Sprague Sargent.
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Looking across the pond to the house.
  - 1900. Photo by Thomas E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Pond. Estate of the late Prof. Charles Sprague Sargent.
  - 1916. Photo by Ralph W. Curtis. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Berberis vulgaris, Syringa chinensis, Wisteria chinensis.
  - 1916. Photo by Ralph W. Curtis. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Acer palmatum.
  - 1916. Photo by Ralph W. Curtis. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Azalea kaempferi.
  - 1923. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Magnolia kobus var. borealis.
  - 1923. Photo by A. E. Christiansen. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron davidsonianum.
  - 1925. Photo by H. W. Gleason. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Narcissus poeticus. Estate of the Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1925. Photo by H. W. Gleason. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Quercus alba. Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1925. Photo by H. W. Gleason. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron wellsianum. Estate of the Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1925? Photo by H. W. Gleason. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Syringa (Lilacs). Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1925? Photo by H. W. Gleason. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Syringa (Lilacs). Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 1926. Photo by A. Seeger. Kurume azalea and Rhododendron sanderi. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Estate of C. S. Sargent.
  - 1926. Photo by A. Seeger. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron indicum var balsaminalflorum. Estate of C. S. Sargent in Brookline.
  - 1926. Photo by A Seeger. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron Sanderi 'Alice Sargent'
  - 1927. Photo by E. H. Wilson. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Magnolia denudata.
  - 192? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Garden Path and Irises. Estate of Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 192? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendrons. Estate of the Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 192? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendrons. Estate of the Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 192? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendrons and pond. Estate of the Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 1933. Photo by T. E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Pond.
  - 1933. Photo by T. E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. View across the Pond. Rhododendrons in the foreground.
  - 1933. Photo by T. E. Marr. Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rhododendron Ignatius Sargent. Estate of late C. S. Sargent in Brookline.
    Rhododendrons in the rear of the old Codman House on the estate.
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Syringa vulgaris var. ?Estate of the late C. S. Sargent.
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Malus floribunda. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Malus floribunda. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Narcissus poeticus, with Salix fragilis, Malus floribunda and Azaleas. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Fothergilla. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Rockery Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - 19?? Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Norway spruce hedge. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Spring Garden. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. View across the pond to Prof. Sargent's house. Malus floribunda in left foreground.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. The Pond. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Kalmia latifolia.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Tsuga canadensis. Sargent Estate.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Poet's Narcissus.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Field of Narcissi. Estate of the late Prof. C. S. Sargent.
  - Holm Lea, Brookline, MA. Lilac garden.
    A rare Tree Peony is shown in from of the scarlet poppies.
  - Certificates & Awards (Box 4:)
- II: Correspondence 1882-1923
  Letters From Charles S. Sargent are housed in 9 bound volumes and are handwritten or typed copies of the originals. The volume numbers do not follow a chronological order. The subject "General" refers to typical arboretum business, such as taxonomy, accessions (requests for and discussions of material), exploration (US and foreign), herbarium (requests for and discussions of material), and accounts. A searchable index to the Sargent correspondence is available on the Arnold Arboretum Library site at http://www.arboretum.harvard.edu/library/lib_search.html.
  - March 1882 - April 1884 Subject: General., Vol I:
  - August 1911 - March 1923 Subject: Library- requests and discussions., Vol II:
  - April 1906 - March 1908 Subject: General- focus on foreign plant exploration, plans and results, and plant accessions., Vol III:
  - April 1906 - August 1911 Subject: Library- requests and discussions., Vol IV:
  - April 1906 - March 1912 Subject: Crataegus- taxonomy, papers, and accessions., Vol V:
    (Inserted: photocopied letters to W. N. Suksdorf concerning Crataegus, 1904, 1905, 1916 (from Washington State University).
  - April 1908 - January 1911 Subject: General- focus on taxonomy and plant accessions., Vol VI:
  - January 1911 - February 1914 Subject: General- focus on US exploration and taxonomy., Vol VII:
  - February 1914 - March 1917 Subject: General., Vol VIII:
  - March 1917 - March 1920 Subject: General- focus on herbarium and US exploration., Vol IX:
- III: Plant Collection Notes
  - (Box 1)
  - Folder 1:
    - 1892. Sargent's collection notes: Seeds sent from Japan by Charles Sprague Sargent, 1892.
      Seeds listed in alphabetical order, no numbers.
    - Collection notes: "of Crataegus, 1900."
    - Charles S. Sargent's Collections
      Dr. Weaver's List of Living Accessions derived from propagating material collected by CSS.
  - Folder 2:
    - "Census. Catalogue of Woods Received."
      Handwritten list numbered 1-1231.
  - Folder 3:
    - Sargent, Charles Sprague. List of Crataegus seed sown in the Arnold Arboretum 1899-1927, no. 1-4514; with manuscript notes by C. S. Sargent.
      Lists 4518 seed collection sown, with collection location and specific epithet.
- IV: Sargent Publications
  - Annotated Bibliography & Articles (Box 1)
  - Folder 1:
    - Labels for the Jesup Wood Collection compiled by Charles S. Sargent
      Removed from the Attic of the Administration Building 1953.
  - Folder 2:
    - Annotated Bibliography
  - Folder 3:
    Bound volume of collected works, spine title: Sargent- Various Articles. Handwritten table of contents with articles numbered.
    - 1874. "Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum.", No.1
    - 1875. "A Few Suggestions on Tree Planting. Report of Massachusetts State Board of Agriculture.", No.2
    - 1876. "Prizes for Arboriculture.Offered by the Trustees of the Massachusetts Society for Promoting Agriculture.", No.3
    - 1878. "Notes on Trees and Tree Planting. 25th Annual Report of the Secretary of the Board of Agriculture.", No.4
    - 1878." Forests: Their Influence on Climate and Soil." By Charles W. Parsons., No.5
    - 1879. The Forests of Central Nevada with Some Remarks on those of Adjacent Regions. American Journal of Science and Arts v.17., No.6
    - 1879-1880. Annual Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum., No.7
    - 1880-1881. Annual Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum., No.8
    - 1881-1882. Annual Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum., No.9
    - 1882. The Protection of Forests. North American Review, October., No.10
    - 1882-1883. Annual Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum., No.11
    - 1883. Forest Fires. 30th Annual Report of the Secretary of the Board of Agriculture., No.12
    - 1881. "Forests, North American.", No.13
    - 1884. Botanical Papers of George Engelmann. Botanical Gazette 9:5., No.14
    - 1883-1884. Report of the Director of the Arnold Arboretum., No.15
    - 1883. Report of the Forestry Commission to the Assembly of New York State. January 23., No.16
    - 1908. Das Arnold Arboretum. Sonder-Abruck aus Mitteilugen der Deutschen. Dendrologischen Gesellschaft, No.17
    - November 1917. The Arnold Arboretum What It Is and Does. The Garden Magazine.
    - May 12, 1915. The Arnold Arboretum. Harvard Alumni Bulletin.
    - 1883. Forest Fires. Thirtieth Annual Report of the Secretary of the Board of Agriculture.
  - Folder 4:, Crataegus Publications by C. S. Sargent
    - February 1901. Notes of Crataegus in the Champlain Valley. Rhodora 3:26.
    - April 1901. Notes on a Collection of Crataegus made in the Province of Quebec, near Montreal. Rhodora 3:28.
    - February 1903. Recently Recognized Species of Crataegus in Eastern Canada of New England, I. Rhodora 5:50.
    - April 1903. Recently Recognized Species of Crataegus in Eastern Canada of New England, II. Rhodora 5:52.
    - May 1903. Recently Recognized Species of Crataegus in Eastern Canada of New England, III. Rhodora 5:53.
    - June and July 1903. Recently Recognized Species of Crataegus in Eastern Canada of New England, V. Rhodora 5:54-55.
    - September-November 1905. Recently Recognized species of Crateagus in Eastern Canada of New England,VI. Rhodora 7:81-83.
    - February 1903. The Genus Crataegus in Newcastle, Delaware. Botanical Gazette v.35.
    - Crataegus in Rochester, New York. Proceedings of the Rochester Academy of Science 4:93-136.
    - June 1903. Crataegus in Northeastern Pennsylvania. Botanical Gazette 35:377-404.
    - September 1905. Crataegus in Eastern Pennsylvania. Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.
    - 1905. Sargent, Charles S. and C. H. Peck. Species of Crataegus Within Twenty Miles of Albany. New York State Museum Bulletin 105. Report of the State Botanist.
    - 1907. Crataegus in Southern Michigan. State Board of Geological Survey.
    - August 1907. Crataegi of Ontario. Ontario Natural Science Bulletin: Journal of the Wellington Field Naturalist's Club No. 3.
    - 1908. Crataegus in Southern Ontario. Ontario Natural Science Bulletin No. 4.
    - 1908. Crataegus in Missouri. 19th Annual Report of the Missouri Botanical Garden.
    - 1907. Some Additions to the Crataegus Flora of Western New York. New York State Museum Bulletin 122, Report of the State Botanist.
    - 1912. Crataegus in New York. New York State Museum Bulletin 167, Report of the State Botanist pp. 53-124.
    - March 1990. Crataegus in Pennsylvania, II. Proceeding of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia pp.150-253.
  - Brief Guides, Reports and Articles (Box 2:)
  - Folder 1:
    - Sargent, C. S. and F. L. Olmsted. November 1880. " Proposition as to the Public Ground to include the Harvard Arboretum."
  - Folder 2:
    - 1891. Publisher's flyer on Garden and Forest.
  - Folder 3:
    - 1907. Sargent, Charles S. et al. Report of the Park Commissioners and the Committee on Planting Trees of Brookline, Massachusetts, 1907. pp. 211-218.
  - Folder 4: